Maddy: Whenever you have a group of people
working together, sooner or later there will
be some form of conflict that will have to
be resolved, even if it’s only minor issues.
So, in this video we are going to be
discussing how important it is that a
manager promotes a positive atmosphere to
minimise the adverse effects of conflict.
Phillip: Although conflict is inevitable,
steps can be taken to help prevent
conflicts from emerging in the first place.
If you do this, you can save time,
energy and resources that would otherwise
be spent minimising and resolving the
conflict once it’s already broken out.
Maddy: One of the best things you can do
to make conflicts less likely to occur,
and less harmful when they do occur, is to
create a positive atmosphere in the workplace
A negative workplace atmosphere can often be
a consequence of an unresolved conflict or
conflicts causing people to have lower morale.
This can in turn lead to the change of
future conflict becoming more likely.
Employees won’t be as enthusiastic about work
and will be less willing to find solutions
to their problems with their colleagues.
With a positive workplace
atmosphere, things are different.
Morale is higher, people will feel happier
and more energised, more enthusiastic
about work, and often more valued.
It also minimises the chances of conflicts
occurring, as people will be more open with
each other and more focused on their jobs.
So, what steps can be taken to
promote a positive atmosphere at work?
Phillip: Arrange Social Events and Mixers
This will encourage people in the team
to unwind and let off some steam, helping
to make them more relaxed and happier.
More importantly, it can also encourage
members of a team to learn more about
each other, outside of the work context.
This can help form friendships and
improve interpersonal relationships,
helping them see each other as real
people instead of just work colleagues.
Maddy: Team Building Activities
Time and budget permitting, running team
building activities like workshops and away
days can help put people together in alternate
situations and encourage them to solve problems.
By putting them in an environment which is not
work related and they have the opportunity to
safely fail and people can learn more about
each other and learn to trust each other more.
It also creates a shared experience and
memory that they can refer back to later.
Phillip: Get to Know Your Team
As a team leader, it’s important to spend time and
make the effort to get to know your team better.
This can help to make you more approachable
to them and help break down the
barriers that can make the relationship
between you and your team impersonal.
If the relationship is friendlier and warmer, the
general attitude of your team will be improved.
Maddy: Encourage Collaboration in the Team
Impress on your team how important it is for
everyone to work together and collaborate.
This will help encourage the team to think
of itself as unified, rather than as divided.
You can do this with a communications campaign,
which can be as simple as emails and posters,
or involve workshops and presentations,
whatever works best for you and your team.
Phillip: Be available to your team
Make sure your team knows you are accessible
and how to reach you if they need to.
Proactively check in with
people to see how they’re doing.
Ask questions and be there to answer
questions that are posed to you.
This will make your team feel like they can
rely on you and make it more likely that they’ll
come to you first if a conflict is starting to
develop, so you can help to nip it in the bud.
Maddy: Remember being a manager or team
leader puts you in a good position to
promote a positive atmosphere when guiding
your team and to so come on, take on
board what we have said and give it a go.